<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on gersti.at</title>
    <link>https://gersti.at/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on gersti.at</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://gersti.at/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>NULL: The Billion Dollar Mistake</title>
      <link>https://gersti.at/posts/billion-dollar-mistake/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gersti.at/posts/billion-dollar-mistake/</guid>
      <description>Overview Link to heading This blog article explores the keyword null, a staple in every programmer&amp;rsquo;s daily work. Should we reconsider the use of null references in our software? Could encountering null in our code actually be harmful? This article aims to address these questions and provide insight into the implications of using null.
Robert Oppenheimer&amp;rsquo;s regret over inventing the atomic bomb serves as a fitting analogy for Tony Hoare&amp;rsquo;s regret over introducing the null reference (Image-Source: Movie: Oppenheimer (2023) by Christopher Nolan).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CQS and CQRS Principles: Splitting the Read from the Write</title>
      <link>https://gersti.at/posts/cqrs/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gersti.at/posts/cqrs/</guid>
      <description>In this blog article, we delve into two essential software design principles: Command and Query Separation (CQS) and Command-Query Responsibility Segregation (CQRS).
An example of separating commands and queries: the left ATM allows you to deposit money (command), and the right one shows your current balance (query).
Command and Query Separation Principle (CQS) Link to heading CQS was introduced by Bertrand Meyer in 1994. As the creator of the programming language Eiffel, he also pioneered the concept of &amp;ldquo;Design by Contract&amp;rdquo; (DbC), which I explored in greater detail in a recent blog post – See: Here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Polymorphism and dynamic binding</title>
      <link>https://gersti.at/posts/polymorphism/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gersti.at/posts/polymorphism/</guid>
      <description>By changing its color, a chameleon can take on different states – similar to an object in programming (Source: Pexels).
Overview Link to heading Polymorphism, along with encapsulation and inheritance, is a fundamental concept of object-oriented programming. But what exactly is polymorphism? This blog article aims to answer that question. Essentially, there are two types of polymorphism – static and dynamic polymorphism.
Static Polymorphism (Compile-Time Polymorphism) Link to heading This is normal method overloading.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Adapter Pattern</title>
      <link>https://gersti.at/posts/adapter-pattern/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gersti.at/posts/adapter-pattern/</guid>
      <description>This blog post offers an explanation of Adapter Design Pattern by Gang of Four. The examples are written in Java.
Visualization of the Adapter Pattern (Source: Refactoring-Guru)
Intent Link to heading The original GoF Design Pattern book defines the Adapter Pattern as follows: Converts the interface of a class into another interface clients expect. Adapter lets classes work together that couldn&amp;rsquo;t otherwise because of incompatible interfaces.
In other words: The adapter pattern is making two interfaces compatible, that aren&amp;rsquo;t compatible.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Liskov substitution principle and DbC in depth</title>
      <link>https://gersti.at/posts/liskov-substitution-principle/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gersti.at/posts/liskov-substitution-principle/</guid>
      <description>This blog post offers a detailed explanation of the liskov substitution principle and gives an overview of the rules you should follow as a software engineer when dealing with inheritance in object-oriented programming to produce clean code. The following is a summary of some sources I have read however also includes my own opinion and knowledge on that topic. Code examples are written in Java.
Overview Link to heading The Liskov Substitution Principle (LSP) was first introduced by Barbara Liskov in 1987 in her article &amp;ldquo;Data Abstraction and Hierarchy&amp;rdquo; and is one of the five SOLID design principles of object-oriented programming.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Strategy Pattern</title>
      <link>https://gersti.at/posts/strategy-pattern/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gersti.at/posts/strategy-pattern/</guid>
      <description>This blog post offers an explanation of Strategy Design Pattern by Gang of Four. The examples are written in Java.
A duck can fly and quack (and can do probably much more things). Image-Source: Pixabay
The Problem that the strategy pattern solves Link to heading Let&amp;rsquo;s say we have a Duck class. And then we have a CityDuck (living in the city) and a WildDuck (living in the forest). We use inheritance – so CityDuck and WildDuck inherit from Duck.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stream API</title>
      <link>https://gersti.at/posts/stream-api/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gersti.at/posts/stream-api/</guid>
      <description>A stream in a forest (Source: Pexels).
Overview Link to heading Java Streams were introduced in Java 8 and are a very powerful concept. They provide a set of functions that you can perform on certain data structures. They allow you to quickly and conveniently perform operations on them. Streams themselves are not data structures and they do not modify the underlying data structures they are operating on.
Streams do all the heavy lifting for you.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Singleton Pattern - A code smell?</title>
      <link>https://gersti.at/posts/singleton-pattern/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gersti.at/posts/singleton-pattern/</guid>
      <description>This blog post offers an explanation of Singleton Design Pattern by Gang of Four. The examples are written in Java.
A comic depicting the Singleton Pattern (Source: Refactoring-Guru). Singleton ensures that there is only ONE single instance of an object. Clients may not even realize that they’re working with the same object all the time.
Intent Link to heading The original GoF Design Pattern book defines the Singleton Pattern as follows: Ensure a class only has one instance, and provide a global point of access to it.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
